Benjamin Luft collection of 9-11 first responders' oral histories
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 1: Oral History Interviews, April 9, 2010 through November 4, 2016
  - Daivd Pachter oral history interview conducted by Dr. Benjamin Luft, April 8, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 201
    David was a Project Executive with IBM Corporation, taking over and managing the IT work flow and networking for major corporations. On September 11th, David and his wife were in West Palm Beach Florida caring for his dad, and helping to get him back into his own home after surgery. They were told about the events by a friend of his fathers, and turned on the television just after the first plane had hit. He felt totally alone and was afraid for his children, two of whom were in Manhattan. He wanted to be a positive force as part of the rebuilding. He was brought up to be a caring person. He could smell the smoke at his home all the way out in Bellmore, NY, and couldn’t sit doing nothing. He felt strongly that he would roll up his sleeves and participate, to do what was right in his gut. He first volunteered with the Salvation Army at the end of October helping children who had lost a parent in the disaster. The kids broke his heart. The sadness on the kid’s faces was overwhelming; their emotions far exceeded anything he could have done for them. The kids did eventually smile, when given a gift, and this touched his heart. He felt close to the kids, it felt good to give them a glimmer of joy. When David’s time working with the kids came to an end, he signed up to go to Ground Zero. He would drive to Manhattan on Friday nights, arriving at Ground Zero between 9 and 10pm and staying overnight until 7 or 8am – this was his routine every Friday for six months. It was surreal approaching Ground Zero the first time. He drove his own car, taking the route he would usually take to Manhattan, and there were police on the Brooklyn Bridge, patrols watching the cars. Generators, spot lights, police barricades, rubble – it no longer felt like Manhattan. It felt like a bombed out war zone. Everything was grey, ash covered everything. He saw trucks, police cars, firefighter trucks all smashed like toy trucks. His job at Ground Zero was to take care of the firefighters, police, and National Guard who were guarding the perimeter. They would bring candy and hot chocolate to the responders, making sure they were comfortable. He had a hard hat that he asked the responders he worked with to sign. He is very proud of this hat, and has it on display in his home till this day. David and his wife were given tickets to attend the 9/11 Memorial. When approaching the Memorial, there appeared to be protesters and he wondered why anyone would protest. As they got closer, they realized that the crowds of people were not protesting - they were thanking the responders for their work at Ground Zero. He became emotional, and said it was the best gift he could have ever been given.
    - Moving Images
    - Graphic Materials
    - Manuscripts
  - John Eberhardt oral history interview conducted by Dr. Benjamin Luft, April 9, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 202
    On 9/11/2001, John was employed by a large printer company, and worked as technician installing and servicing their equipment. He had previous training with the Red Cross, and volunteered as a Disaster Assistance Technician for five weeks during the Rescue and Recovery efforts post 9/11. As he recalled all the events, his vivid memories still made him emotional, but he is proud of his time served. His only regret was not wearing his respirator “at all times”. That morning, John was in Northport on his way to a job site, when he heard on the radio that a plane hit one of the towers. He found that to be odd because of his aviation knowledge and knew that it was an “impossible feat for two planes, to hit two buildings within minutes of each other”. After seeing the footage on a portable TV, he knew it was no accident. John’s employer allowed him to leave work early, and he returned home where he lived alone with his dog in Huntington, LI. He can still remember the burnt scent in the air, even though he was 40 miles away from Ground Zero. He was also able to see the plume of smoke that emerged from the site. John’s immediate response to this catastrophe was being compelled to do whatever he could to help. He learned that due to Red Cross politics, because his local chapter (Nassau-Suffolk) wasn’t “invited” to go to Ground Zero, then he could not serve there, so he went on his own with his Red Cross ID. On 9/13/11, he took the LIRR and subway to Canal Street, and preceded on foot the “Dead Zone”. His first visual memory coming up the stairs of the subway station is a black car covered with gray dust with “Bin Laden Die” written by finger (of which he has a picture of). He describes the first few days of the rescue effort as “organized chaos”. He would work at his day job, then volunteer from 4pm to sunrise, return home to sleep for a few hours and return the next day, and continued this schedule for five weeks. Only police, fire, ironworkers and special agencies were allowed on “the pile,” so John was only allowed to work the perimeter. He stationed himself with the local Red Cross truck that was parked at the South Tower. One of the most important jobs he had, being a dog lover, was helping the “Sniffer Dogs”. Their paws needed protection from the heat of the pile, eyewash from the gray dust and food and water. If the workers or dogs thought they found any signs of life, they would blow the air horn three times, then all equipment would shut down and they would wait to hopefully hear something. When Rescue changed to Recovery, John assisted the workers who were on the extension ladder trucks spraying water on Building 7, because it was a “hot spot”. John would also retrieve cigarettes for the ironworkers who would request specific brands (i.e.: Marlboro, Pall Mall, Winston). While John was volunteering, he managed to fracture his foot. Then in February of 2002, John was diagnosed with severe GERD, which affected his singing voice. Then in 2013, was diagnosed with lung cancer. Since he has lived his life as a vegetarian for the past 40 years, is a non-smoker, non-drinker, and is a physically fit runner, he and his doctors are convinced that his diagnoses are directly associated with the grey and black dust that surrounded him while he volunteered. He knew the EPA was constantly monitoring the air, and although the authorities stated the air quality was “adequate”, there was also an “array of chemicals that could not be identified”. Luckily, he has been able to successfully be treated for both conditions, and is doing well. John’s entire experience has showed him “how well humans work together under duress”. He did not make any long term friendships from his time there, but was proud of the comradery that everyone displayed. He realizes that many people in the world do not like the United States, and we should “practice what we preach”.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Glenn Tarquinio oral history interview conducted by Dr. Benjamin Luft, April 11, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 203
    Glenn was a NYPD Officer on 9/11 and is currently with Suffolk County PD. Even though he was the first in his family to become a police officer, he has two brothers who are police officers and another brother who was a firefighter. All of them were in these positions during 9/11. On the day of the attacks, Glenn was called into work. Before leaving his home in Nesconset, Long Island, he gathered all his important documents that he had locked up and gave them to his wife, not knowing what he was getting himself into. As he was driving in towards NYC, he saw the cloud of smoke from the Long Island Expressway in Melville (Route 110). One of the things that he always remembered when getting to his precinct was seeing the officers coming off the previous shift. There weren’t as many guys that day coming off their shift. Glenn and his fellow officers were transported to the South Street Seaport. He wasn’t too familiar downtown Manhattan, and as he was by the WTC area, he saw a building that was about 6 stories high at that point, which kind of had the outside peeled off. He originally thought that this was one of the towers, but found out that this was really 7 WTC. The whole area was like a “movie set”. While at Ground Zero, when they sounded the horns three times, it meant that there was there was an adjacent building that was unstable and may collapse. The horns meant they were supposed to run away from the area due to the possibility of the nearby building coming down, and Glenn recalls his colleague running so fast that his shoes literally came off. He was part of the bucket brigade lines, trying to find body parts. He was there when they found the last person alive; the person was filled with dust and everyone clapped as he was lifted out. This gave Glenn a sense of purpose to his work down there. Any body parts that were found were treated with dignity. As the effort changed to recovery, there were tons of photos of loved ones posted on the security fences for the responders to try and find. They would try to find anything, body parts or material belongings, to bring some type of closure for loved ones; there was a lot riding on what they were doing there in terms of recovery. He once found a note “Son’s Little League Game at 7 O'clock”. He personalized this, not knowing if the person was alive or not, and imagined the father going to the kids baseball game with his tie and suite jacket off after a long day of work or not showing up. He knew personalizing these things was a dangerous thing to do, but it’s what he did. Glenn says that it was difficult to see that many body part; he’s never seen so many and hopes he never does again. There was a change in viewpoint towards NYPD Officers during this time by the public. This was nice because people actually respected them as police officers and this also pushed him during this time. Three years prior to 9/11, Glenn studied Criminal Justice and minored in Psychology in college. That gave him the education to be part of POPPA (Police Officers Providing Peer Assistance) and MAP (Members Assistance Program). He talked with fellow officers about their experiences for therapeutic purposes. This was difficult but helped many officers tremendously. Glenn lost a friend of his from work, Tommy Langone, from NYPD ESU, and his Glenn’s brother, FDNY Firefighter, just recently passed away from 9/11 related illness(es). Today, Glenn appreciates the little things in life like the changing of seasons and doesn’t worry about the things that are out of his control. Glenn ends off by saying, “Mean what you say and say what you mean.”
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Joeseph F. Eduardo oral history interview conducted by Brittain Mahaffey, April 11, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 204
    Joseph was a Verizon Field Engineer on 9/11/2001 and worked the midtown Manhattan area. He wasn’t with Verizon for too long and was only 26 years old but worked his way up the organization quickly and held this supervising position. Joseph recalls that Tuesday morning being a clear day and hearing a news reporter saying, “It was a good day to fly” early in the morning before the towers were hit. Later in the morning (still early), they were listening to the Howard Stern Show on the radio and he heard tons of sirens out his window. He eventually heard something in regards to what was happening at the WTC, and he went up to the roof of his midtown Manhattan building with a colleague to get a first-hand look at what was happening. Joseph got up to the roof after the 1st plane hit and witnessed the first tower collapsing. When they went back downstairs, it was very chaotic as people were finding out what was happening. He was initially advised to help with setting up a triage center at Bryant Park, but they quickly realized that there wouldn’t be much use for the triage center. He got asked if he would stay the night to help with whatever was needed in terms of communications. He agreed to do it. Later in the day on 9/11/2001, he took a Verizon Van with his colleague (which he would never be allowed to do if it weren’t a disaster of this magnitude) and drove down to the Verizon building at 140 West Street. Joseph says it was like a movie scene down by the WTC area. No one was around, which was very atypical of the area and Manhattan in general. The building they were staying at, 140 West Street, was completely damaged since it was adjacent to the towers. They had a bunch of underground equipment at this location that was all damaged. There was a layer of dust covering everything and they didn’t have any respirators or masks to wear. Joseph snagged a piece of paper that was within all the debris. It was part of a Stock Broker’s Manual and was page number “9-11”. He still has this paper to this day (see picture attached to Joseph’s interview). Joseph stayed the night with an impromptu bed that they rigged up. At times, he wasn’t sure exactly what he was supposed to be doing down there. Eventually, Joseph worked on getting the stock market back up and running. He drew the plans for the fiber optic wiring that the stock market needed. He understood the importance of this for the economy but was still a little discouraged that this was such a priority. Joseph also setup a command post at the front of FDNY 10 Engine – 10 Truck. At this point, he was wearing a white Tyvek suit, but still no respirator. Joseph is now an FDNY Firefighter and has been for 10 years now. He talks about the decision of leaving his job at Verizon to be a firefighter with the FDNY; he saw all that the firefighters did on 9/11 and probably wouldn’t have decided to become a firefighter if he not had this experience at the WTC site during 9/11.
    - Moving Images
    - Graphic Materials
    - Manuscripts
  - Marcelo Gallina oral history interview conducted by Julie Broihier, April 15, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 205
    Marcelo was an officer with the NYPD working in midtown Manhattan on 9/11/2001, on what he calls a beautiful morning. At the time of the attacks, he was writing a traffic ticket for a minor infraction when he heard on the radio that a plane had crashed downtown. As it turns out, he was writing the ticket at the exact moment the first plane hit; he keeps that ticket as a memento to this day. Although his first instinct was to rush to the scene, his partner convinced him to stay and wait for orders. They were soon recalled to the station, where Marcelo was assigned to assist in the evacuation of the Empire State Building, one of many public landmarks located within the precinct. During this job, he recalls hearing the voice of officer Morris Smith calling for help from within the towers: “She was basically dying on the radio… She did what we all wanted to do, and she paid with her life.” Although he was not at the World Trade Center on 9/11, he watched one of the towers fall from the steps of the New York City Post Office. The next day, he was assigned to site security detail, stopping passersby and onlookers from getting too near to the pile. At the site, there were several buildings that were still standing but could fall at any moment. If they were going to fall, a horn would sound, and anyone in the area had to run for their lives. Marcelo recalls being more scared than he had ever been before when he heard one of those horns sound and he began to run; to this day he hasn’t been as scared as in that moment. Marcelo worked at Ground Zero every few days; on the other days, he rotated between other site security details, protecting religious institutions and other sensitive areas. For him, it’s the memories of the little things that stick with him the most. For instance, he remembers seeing fighter jets flying over Manhattan in the days following the attacks, and entering the wrong tent at Ground Zero and seeing firefighters’ oxygen tanks completely melted and burned. He still keeps in touch with several people whom he worked with at the site, and they rarely talk about 9/11 anymore. For them, it’s also about the little things, like the comfort centers that were set up at St. John’s and a nearby Marriott. Marcelo also explicitly mentions that one of his closest friends passed away in 2005 due to 9/11-related illness. He also singles out culture of police officers and firefighters to “put on a tough exterior” despite their anguish as something that is changing and must continue to change. Marcelo believes the world has been changed by the attacks, especially the United States. “Just go to an airport and tell me things aren’t different now,” he says. He sees himself as having been a very small part of a world-changing event, and hopes that the world will become a better place as we learn lessons from the attacks and their aftermath.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Robert Zawacki oral history interview conducted by Melodie Guerrera, April 17, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 206
    Robert, a veteran of the Vietnam War, was working in his office in midtown Manhattan on 9/11/2001. When the first plane hit, he didn’t think much of it, believing it to be a small plane accident. Once he realized that it was an attack, he made sure that everyone who depended on him would be safe and taken care of. He and his company made arrangements for their employees to stay in hotels, then he made his way uptown to take his daughter out of school. A coworker was able to take them via back roads out of New York City to their home in Westchester County. The next morning, Robert saw Mayor Giuliani’s call for volunteers who knew first aid and went into the city to volunteer. On his way to the Javits Center, he saw a sign for the Salvation Army requesting volunteers and signed up with them instead. When they arrived at Ground Zero, he was immediately struck by the odor in the air, which he likened to the poison gas the US Army would use to flush out Viet Cong members before he and his men would drop into the jungles. During those operations, they wore full gas masks, so the paper painter’s masks that they were issued were simply not good enough in his view. He received a full gas mask from a departing federal agent, which he wore the whole time he was there. Robert spent two full days on site, handing out water, ice, and food to responders who needed them. During that time, he never stopped to sleep, although he did take breaks every so often. He felt his training in the armed forces prepared him for the stress of being among the wreckage, and was disturbed not merely because such a heinous act had occurred, but because it had occurred in the United States. Robert empathizes with and respects the first responders that are now suffering from health problems simply from doing their jobs, because he himself contracted cancer from the Agent Orange chemical agent during his time in Vietnam. He doesn’t see himself as a hero for responding to the events of 9/11 as he did, but rather sees that response as a “natural instinct of helping.” He believes that, in the future, the safety of civil servants should be a higher priority for the government, should such an event befall the country again.
    - Moving Images
  - Joseph Ferramosca oral history interview conducted by Dr. Benjamin Luft, April 18, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 207
    Joseph was a captain in the New York Department of Corrections, working at headquarters at 60 Hudson Street, on 9/11/2001. He was at work when one of his co-workers told him that a plane had flown into the World Trade Center. At that time, he notes, nobody was really sure what had happened or why; it wasn’t until much later that he became aware that the events were part of an attack. Joseph is one of the only members of his family who is involved in law enforcement, and believes that his training as a correctional officer is how he was able to run to the site of the attacks and suppress his fear to offer help to people who needed him. When an alarm is sounded in a prison, he said, correctional officers must run toward the alarm, not away, and be prepared to face whatever they find, no matter how dangerous or frightening. On the day of the attacks, Joseph, his boss, and two of his subordinates made their way to the towers. Joseph remembers the “white noise” of people screaming and the sight of people jumping from the windows as the towers burned. Although one of his officers told him to not look up, Joseph couldn’t help but watch. In his own words, “how could [I] not?” Even today, if he closes his eyes, he can still see the image of those people falling from the windows. After a little time had passed, the first tower began to fall. That moment, he recalls, was one where he truly felt afraid for his life, because he couldn’t see the tower and was afraid that it might crush him and everyone he was with. Additionally, although he does not remember many sounds from that day besides “white noise,” he does recall one specific sound from that tower collapsing: a sound akin to a metal pot being dropped onto the floor. He suggests that the sound was the sound of the top of the building hitting the ground. He and his colleagues ducked into an elementary school soon thereafter, where the children were lined in up rows of two by the teachers, whom he recalled were “scared” but “extraordinary.” They helped evacuate the school, then made their way back outside and moved closer to where the towers stood. They then assisted with the evacuation of a brick building next to 5 World Trade Center, collaborating with the FDNY to clear out people on the upper floors who had broken out their windows. After this, two of his colleagues went back to 60 Hudson, and he remained with one of his officers. They then ran across a man on the street and helped evacuate him and his family from their nearby second-floor apartment. He also recalls a man who was trying to cross the police line and enter the enclosed area on West Broadway to find his wife. The man was insistent that he must enter the fray to look for her, despite Joseph telling him that he was not allowed through. Eventually, Joseph told him, “Nobody’s down there. We got everybody out. Your wife is somewhere, on her way home. I know she is.” To this day, he still wonders if that man went home to his wife. Another aspect that he will always remember is the “smell of death” that lingered in the air throughout the day, a smell which he first experienced as a 16-year-old. Joseph does not characterize himself as a “talking” kind of person, so he has spent a lot of time trying to come to grips with the events of 9/11 on his own. That day, on his way back to HQ after the events described above, he sat in a park just above the Hudson/W Broadway split for 10 minutes “just to get a grip on what happened.” In the years since, he has kept a journal that he only shared with one other person in thirteen years. His last entry was on the tenth anniversary of the attacks, three years ago. Today, he is grateful for and more appreciative of what he has than he was before the attacks, and wishes more of the world would take the same perspective – as they did, in his eyes, in the days and months immediately following the attacks. That, he says, would be his message to the world in the aftermath of 9/11/2001.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Don Mathisen oral history interview conducted by Dr. Benjamin Luft, April 22, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 208